Guide to the Santerre collection of Charles X, 1535-1855
Santerre collection of Charles X, 1535-1855
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Santerre collection of Charles X, 1535-1855 (bulk 1773-1830)
4603
Charles X, King of France, 1757-1836.
10.2 linear ft.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Business correspondence, accounts, statements, receipts, vouchers, deeds, transcripts of transactions, and notes, mainly written or collected by the personal or family treasurers of the Comte d'Artois (including his reign as King Charles X) and of his grandson, the count of Chambord and duke of Bordeaux. The collection documents the management of the Comte d'Artois's personal and household finances from 1773 until his permanent exile following the July Revolution of 1830, with documents concerning some family estates extending back to 1535. It also documents the management of the Comte de Chambord's personal and household finances through 1855. Most items are from the pre-Revolutionary period (1773-1789), the Restoration (1814-1830), or items concerning the Comte de Chambord (from 1828-1855), including expenses for his education and begging letters received by him or his tutors. Materials from Restoration period include a complete set of annual accounts of the Comte d'Artois's household from 1815-1830.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Count of Artois; King of France 1824-1830.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Business correspondence, accounts, statements, receipts, vouchers, deeds, transcripts of transactions, and notes, mainly written or collected by the personal or family treasurers of the Comte d'Artois (including his reign as King Charles X) and of his grandson, the count of Chambord and duke of Bordeaux. The collection documents the management of the Comte d'Artois's personal and household finances from 1773 until his permanent exile following the July Revolution of 1830, with documents concerning some family estates extending back to 1535. It also documents the management of the Comte de Chambord's personal and household finances through 1855. Most items are from the pre-Revolutionary period (1773-1789), the Restoration (1814-1830), or items concerning the Comte de Chambord (from 1828-1855), including expenses for his education and begging letters received by him or his tutors. Materials from Restoration period include a complete set of annual accounts of the Comte d'Artois's household from 1815-1830.
Treasurers of the Comte d'Artois or of his family were: Barthélémy Pierre Droüet de Santerre, Anselme Barthélémy Droüet de Santerre, and Henri Louis de Belleville. Correspondents include them and Baron Ange-Hyacinthe Maxence de Damas (tutor of the Comte de Chambord), Abbé Tharin (Chambord's preceptor), and the Marquis Amédée-David de Pastoret (administrator of Chambord's possessions after 1840).
SUBJECTS
Names:
Charles X, King of France, 1757-1836.; Belleville, Henri Louis de.; Chambord, Henri-Charles-Ferdinand-Marie-Dieudonné d'Artois, 1820-1883.; Damas, Ange-Hyacinthe-Maxence, 1785-1862.; Pastoret, Amédée-David, 1791-1851.; Santerre, Anselme Barthélémy Droüet de.; Santerre, Barthélémy Pierre Droüet de, 1734-1818.; Tharin, abbé.
Subjects:
Land tenure--France--History.; Land titles--Registration and transfer--France--History.; Administration of estates--France--History.; Finance, Personal--France--History.; Education--France--History.; Upper class--Education--France.; Domestic relations--France.
Places:
France--History--Charles X, 1824-1830--Sources.; France--History--Louis XVI, 1774-1793--Sources.; France--History--Restoration, 1814-1830--Sources.; France--Economic conditions--18th century.; France--Economic conditions--19th century.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- A - Bor (Box 1)
- Bordeaux, Henri, duc de. A - N (Box 2)
- Bordeaux, Henri, duc de. O - Z (Box 3)
- Bos - Charles X. C (Box 4)
- Charles X. D - Charles X. Domaines Deeds 1669 (Box 5)
- Charles X. Domaines Deeds 1670 - Charles X. Domaines Obr (Box 6)
- Charles X. Domaines Obs - Charles X. Z (Box 7)
- Charles X. Maison - Charles X. Tresor. Compte (Box 8)
- Charles X. Tresor. Compte de l'Exercise 1776-1826 (Box 9)
- Charles X. Tresor. Compte de l'Exercise 1827 - D (Box 10)
- Charles X. Ea - Charles X. Ew (Box 11)
- Charles X. Ex - Charles X. N (Box 12)
- Charles X. O - Charles X. Rem (Box 13)
- Charles X. Ren - Charles X. Z - Cz (Box 14)
- Daa - Daz (Box 15)
- Dea - Der (Box 16)
- Des - France. A (Box 17)
- France. B (Box 18)
- France. C - France. J (Box 19)
- France. K - Lemerle, A. (decembre 1848) (Box 20)
- Lemerle, A. (janvier 1849 - fevrier 1852) (Box 21)
- Lemerle, A. (mars 1852) - N (Box 22)
- O - Santerre (Box 23)
- Santerre, Anselme (Box 24)
- Santerre, Anselme - Sz (Box 25)
- T-Z (Box 26)